Contact

757-376-8340 (Mobile) arundeepak89@gmail.com

www.linkedin.com/in/arundeepak89 (LinkedIn)

github.com/arundeep89 (Personal)

Top Skills

Data Quality
Datastream
dbt

Languages

English (Full Professional) Hindi (Full Professional)

Certifications

Microsoft Certified: Azure Al Fundamentals

Google Analytics 4 (GA4) Essential Training

Microsoft Certified: Azure Data Engineer Associate

Microsoft Certified: Azure Data Fundamentals

Setting Team and Employee Goals Using SMART Methodology

Honors-Awards

Student Member

Publications

Synthesis and characterization of PbTe thin films by atomic layer deposition

ALD growth of PbTe and PbSe Superlattices for Thermoelectric Applications

Arun Deepak Ramalingom Pillai, PMP

Bringing together People, Business and Technology Greater Toronto Area, Canada

Summary

As a Data Leader with experience working in culturally diverse organizations, I love bringing People, Business and Technology together by simplifying data workflows and helping find real value in data. If you'd like to connect or learn more about my experience, please feel free to send me a message or start a conversation at arundeepak89@gmail.com.

Experience

Skip

Lead Data Engineer August 2022 - Present (3 years)

Ontario, Canada

- Managed enterprise level data products for partner and sales pillar by delivering incremental value in an agile environment. This consisted of collaborating with stakeholders to manage backlogs, facilitating standup's, managing work in progress, resolving conflicts, promoting collective code ownership and providing servant leadership to deliver solutions.
- Established and mentored a team of engineers and analysts on best practices for developing pipelines, data modelling/warehousing, data quality/ governance, data analytics/visualization while maintaining SLA's to deliver on data-driven initiatives.
- Analyzed source systems and developed 50+ data pipelines to transfer data from Salesforce Marketing Cloud, Braze, AppAnnie, PostgreSQL, MySQL, DynamoDB, etc to Google Cloud Storage/Google BigQuery by orchestrating via Airflow with 99.99% reliability and an average downtime of 10 minutes per month. In addition to batch ingestion, also worked on real time data ingestion from kafka topics.
- Partnered with global data teams to define and adopt medallion architecture (bronze, silver and gold layer) that establishes a single source of truth per domain using dbt. This provided optimized data workflows, automatic SQL

documentation, data quality checks, automation using macros and code reusability.

- Supported development of semantic modelling layer by defining dimensions, aggregates, calculations and data relationships to enable ad-hoc self-serve reporting and data exploration for the business thereby enabling analysts to focus on the most important business initiatives.
- Provisioned GCP infrastructure (BigQuery tables, Storage buckets, Datastream, Cloud Functions, IAM, etc) using Terraform (Infrastructure as Code).
- Utilized version control system such as GitHub to track changes, support collaboration, and ensure code integrity throughout every development process. GitHub Actions was used for automated deployment following CI/CD principles.

Innovation Credit Union Senior Data Modeler May 2021 - August 2022 (1 year 4 months) Ontario, Canada

- Collaborated with stakeholders to define the scope of projects, identify source systems and understand business rules to establish centralized data models for reporting thereby increasing reporting efficiency by 50%.
- Identified gaps between current state and desired future state architectures through gap analysis.
- Built dimensional models such as star schemas, snowflake schemas and fact and dimension tables for data warehouses.
- Established a data governance framework consisting of 5+ data producers and consumers and provided data lineage information for critical business data elements using Purview.
- Serve as a reference and authority on the process of data modeling and ensure consistency with existing standards for data models.
- Collaborated with external consultants to manage project deliverables, oversaw the recruiting, onboarding process and mentored junior BI team members.

 Researched emerging technologies related to Data Modeling, Database Design and Development, ETL processes to create POCs.

Ferguson Enterprises 5 years 9 months

Data Modeler II November 2017 - May 2021 (3 years 7 months) VA, USA

- Built and led the Marketing Technology team responsible for architecting data used by Oracle cloud marketing technology stack tools (Eloqua, Responsys and Bluekai) resulting in 35% reduction in customer acquisition costs.
- Facilitated batch and real time data load/processing using Azure tools such as Data Factory, Azure Functions, Data Lake, Synapse Analytics, SQL database, Stream Analytics, Event Hubs, etc to enable data scientists/data analysts to perform their analyses, resulting in a 30% reduction in time-tosolve.
- Implemented Logic Apps and Azure monitor for error logging and monitoring of data factory pipelines.
- Built the required data models by assimilating data from various sources using SQL queries, stored procedures, etc.
- Enabled data exchange between in-house CRM system and Eloqua, using API's, to support the build out of prospecting campaigns in Eloqua, resulting in an increase of qualified leads by 25%.
- Collaborated with architects, developers, business users and external consultants to develop solutions following agile methodologies such as Scrum and Xtreme Programming to provide impactful outcomes.
- Developed database architectural strategies at modeling, design, and implementation stages to address business and industry requirements.
- Identified and evaluated industry trends to serve as source of information and advice for upper management.
- Championed implementation of CI/CD practices to ensure iterative/ incremental delivery.

 Maintained operational documentation in partnership with technical authors using SharePoint.

Data Modeler I

September 2015 - November 2017 (2 years 3 months)

VA, USA

- Established API solutions that integrate with Quickbase, Silverpop, Wufoo, Weka and Google Sheets to eliminate duplication of work.
- Developed Outlook Add-in capabilities in conjunction with web services to automate repeatable processes thereby increasing efficiency by 40% through saved labor hours.
- Built lead management portal using C# with SQL backend to provide CRM capabilities to Marketing and Sales, thus contributing incremental revenue of around \$500,000 in fiscal year 2017.
- Migrated visualizations to Tableau which augments traditional reporting capabilities thereby enabling better decision making.
- Developed ETL packages with Business Intelligence Studio to automate data loads.
- Monitored Business Intelligence environment and performed unit tests to assess system durability.
- Maintained documentation and provided customer support as required.
- Proficient in Microsoft Office 365 Products.
- Performed User Acceptance Testing (UAT) for transactional websites.

Adecco

Automation Analyst

October 2014 - September 2015 (1 year)

VA, USA

 Worked with client 'Ferguson Enterprises' and developed Outlook Add-in capabilities to automate repeatable processes thereby increasing efficiency by 20% through saved labor hours.

- Developed ETL packages with Business Intelligence Studio to automate data loads.
- Engaged with customers to analyze requirements and developed solutions to solve business problems.
- Maintained documentation and provided customer support as required.

Swisslog

Intern

June 2014 - September 2014 (4 months)

VA, USA

- Tested software in accordance with design requirements.
- Provided documentation support, customer support and organized meetings.

Cognizant Technology Solutions Programmer Analyst Trainee July 2011 - June 2012 (1 year)

Chennai Area, India

- Developed multiple, modular objects and a messaging interface to create a software package that allowed secure access to customer banking details.
- Researched software issues, performed defect corrections, and provided recommended solutions based on code and systems analysis.
- Utilized ASP.Net, ADO.NET, C, C++, C#, JavaScript, CSS, and HTML in .NET Framework 4.0 for the development of banking and finance technologies.

Education

Old Dominion University

Master's degree, Computer Engineering · (2012 - 2014)

Anna University Chennai

Bachelor of Engineering (B.E.), Electrical and Electronics Engineering · (2007 - 2011)